## KAITLIN PERKINS

# SKILLS & ABILITIES

Graduate student in ecology with excellent communication skills, contributing energy, ideas, and enthusiasm. An appreciation of diversity and the ability to learn well from others. Creative, flexible, and determined. Strong leadership and civic engagement. Programming languages include R statistical software, LaTeX, and Excel. Experience in statistical analysis, technical writing, data management, and field and lab work.

#### **GOALS**

Pursue practice and research in aquatic sciences and natural resource management. Objectives are to apply knowledge to tackle complex watershed issues post-MS. Passions include environmental education and outreach.

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### **ECOSYSTEMS LAB, UNIVERSITY OF MONTANA**

Graduate Research Assistant, August 2017 - present

Pursuing Master's in Systems Ecology under the mentorship of Dr. Ben Colman focused on investigating the role of size and particle interactions in metal transport in the Upper Clark Fork River, Montana. Responsibilities include regular sample collection and analysis using size fractionation, dynamic light scattering, and spectrofluorometric analysis.

#### AQUATIC ECOLOGY LAB, WASHINGTON STATE UNIVERSITY VANCOUVER

Undergraduate Researcher, August 2015 - August 2017

Investigating the vertical distribution of phytoplankton in relation to hypoxia in Lacamas Lake under the mentorship of Dr. Gretchen Rollwagen-Bollens. The project was accepted into the University Scholars Honors Program and is a continuation of work accomplished in the REU Program. Research has been accepted by *Lake and Reservoir Management* for publication.

## DIRECTED OCEANOGRAPHIC RESEARCH, SEA SEMESTER, WOODS HOLE & NEW ZEALAND

Student Researcher, September 2014 – December 2014

Researched the density of micro and macroplastics in the ocean waters of New Zealand. Designed and carried out the project with two other students under the guidance of mentor Deb Goodwin. Conducted background research and finalized sampling design on shore, with all sample collection, analysis, and interpretation occurring at sea.

## **EDUCATION**

## MASTER OF SCIENCE IN SYSTEMS ECOLOGY

University of Montana, Missoula, Montana Expected graduation: November 2020

## BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN BIOLOGY, MINORS IN ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE AND MATHEMATICS

Fall 2013 – May 2017

Washington State University Vancouver, Vancouver, Washington

SEA SEMESTER - WOODS HOLE, MA & NEW ZEALAND

September 2014 - December 2014

Global Oceans Program - Oceanography, Conservation, Leadership, and Cultural Studies

Studied in Woods Hole, MA for 6 weeks and on a 135' sailing school research vessel in the waters of New Zealand for 6 weeks. Developed leadership, maintenance, sailing, and navigation skills on the ship through participation as a crew member. Gained research experience through equipment deployment and work in the onboard lab. Rotated as Junior Watch Officer and Junior Lab Officer modeling appropriate safety procedures and maintaining proper ship operations.

#### **ASSOCIATE IN SCIENCE**

Clark College, Vancouver, Washington GPA: 3.0, Graduated Spring 2013

#### **TRAINING**

#### UM BRIDGES TRAINEE, WATER-ENERGY-FOOD NEXUS GRADUATE CERTIFICATE

University of Montana

NSF-funded graduate training program that focuses on applied science at the nexus of food, energy, and water. Training complements thesis research through applied and interdisciplinary skills development. Engaged in classes and workshops focused on science communication, policy, bridging science and practice, and complex issues at the food-energy-water nexus.

#### **CERTIFICATE IN QUANTITATIVE BIOLOGY**

Washington State University Vancouver

Completed combination of upper level mathematics, statistics, and biology coursework.

## WORK EXPERIENCE

#### NATURALIST AND DECKHAND, THE SCHOONER ZODIAC, BELLINGHAM, WA

May 2017 - August 2017

Provide educational materials and assistance for species identification and give presentations about marine ecology and stewardship. Teach passengers sail technique, theory, and navigation. Assist with sailing operations, including ship maintenance, sail handling, navigation, passenger support, and safety.

## NATURAL RESOURCE SPECIALIST ASSISTANT, CLARK COUNTY ENVIRONMENTAL SERVICES

January, 2016 - February 2017

Work in Clean Water Division to conduct clean water outreach, lead in oil/water separator inventory and GIS mapping project, assist with stormwater monitoring field work, assist with data compilation and analysis for stormwater monitoring, field collections of stream water and macroinvertebrate samples, and conduct maintenance on stormwater sampling equipment.

#### SALES AGENT, GREEN MOUNTAIN ENERGY, PORTLAND, OR

February, 2013 - January, 2015

Communicated the operation and benefit of Portland General Electric's renewable energy certificate program to a diverse customer base.

#### GRASSROOTS EDUCATOR, BARK, PORTLAND, OR

September, 2012 - March 2013

Educated citizens about socio-environmental issues in Mt. Hood National Forest.

#### UNDERGRADUATE PHYSICS 201 TEACHING ASSISTANT, CLARK COLLEGE, VANCOUVER, WA

January 2013 - March 2013

Graded physics assignments under the guidance of Dr. Gothard Grey.

#### ASSISTANT, INSTAFAB CO, INC., VANCOUVER, WA

August 2007 - May 2011

Assisted with the family business in project management, material quotes, LEED certification, delivery driving, janitorial, tool room management, supply ordering, and building maintenance.

#### SELECT

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

# **CONFERENCE**

Perkins, K. R. et al. Lake and Reservoir Management Variability in the vertical distribution of chlorophyll PRESENTATIONS in a spill-managed temperate reservoir. Lake and Reservoir Management. 0, 1–8 (2019).

#### &

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Perkins, K, Montaño, M, Colman, B. 5-minute Oral Presentation. Characteristics of submicron particles in a mine-waste contaminated river. CREWS All Hands Meeting, Digital, October 2020.

Perkins, K, Montaño, M, Colman, B. Oral Presentation. Characterizing sub-micron metal particles in a mine waste contaminated river to better understand potential exposure. GradCon, Missoula, MT, January 2020.

Perkins, K, Montaño, M, Colman, B. Poster Presentation, Examining the Abundance and Composition of Submicron Particles in a Mine-waste Contaminated Intermountain West River. EPSCoR National Conference, Columbia, SC, October 2019.

Perkins, K. Montaño, M. Colman, B. Poster Presentation, Examining the Abundance and Composition of Submicron Particles in a Mine-waste Contaminated Intermountain West River. Montana American Water Resources Association, Red Lodge, MT, October 2019.

Perkins, K, Montaño, M, Colman, B. Poster Presentation, Examining the Abundance and Composition of Submicron Particles in a Mine-waste Contaminated Intermountain West River. EPSCoR All Hands Meeting, Butte, MT, October 2019.

Perkins, K, Montaño, M, Colman, B. Poster Presentation, Prospecting for Submicron Metal Particles in a Mine Waste Contaminated. Society for Freshwater Sciences conference, Salt Lake City, UT, May 2019.

Perkins, K, Montaño, M, Colman, B. Poster Presentation, Size, associations, and distribution of mining contaminants in the Upper Clark Fork River, Montana. Montana Aquatic Research Consortium conference, April 2019.

Perkins, K, Montaño, M, Colman, B. Poster Presentation, Size, associations, and distribution of mining contaminants in the Upper Clark Fork River, Montana. Montana EPSCoR conference, February 2019.

Perkins, K, Montaño, M, Colman, B. Poster Presentation, Size, associations, and distribution of mining contaminants in the Upper Clark Fork River, Montana. GradCon, University of Montana, February 2019.

Perkins, K, Rollwagen-Bollens G, Bollens S, Zimmerman, J. Influence of environmental factors on vertical distribution of phytoplankton in Lacamas Lake, WA. Air & Waste Management Association Oregon Chapter Student Environmental Challenge.

Perkins K, Rollwagen-Bollens G, Bollens S, Zimmerman, J. Influence of environmental factors on vertical distribution of phytoplankton in Lacamas Lake, WA. Washington State University Vancouver Research Showcase. April 2016.

Perkins K, Rollwagen-Bollens G, Bollens S, Zimmerman J. Influence of environmental factors on vertical distribution of phytoplankton in Lacamas Lake, WA. Murdock Charitable Trust College Science Research Program, Vancouver, WA. November 2015.

Perkins K, Rollwagen-Bollens G, Bollens S, Zimmerman J. Influence of environmental factors on vertical distribution of phytoplankton in Lacamas Lake, WA. Summer Undergraduate Research Symposium, WSU Vancouver. August 2015.

# LEADERSHIP & CIVIC ENGAGEMENT

Lead organization of Let's Talk About Water Montana film screening and panel discussion, Day of Action, and Science on Tap water talks at Imagine Nation brewing, January 2019 – November 2019

Co-organized two Science, Policy, and Practice panel discussions: a discussion panel on women in government science roles (February 2019) and a discussion panel on women in non-academic science roles (November 2019), collaboration between Graduate Women in Science and Women in Science in Division of Biological Sciences

Founded the Missoula Chapter of the Graduate Women in Science, December 2018

Montana Natural History Center Naturalist in the Classroom volunteer, October 2017 - present

We Are Montana in the Classroom volunteer, October 2017 - present

nPower Girls Watershed Quality Camp Co-leader, Castle Rock, July 2017

Spoke in a video produced for the Clark Community College STEM Department regarding my experiences as a woman in science and mathematics, June 2017

Volunteer tree planter with Friends of Trees, Vancouver, WA, 2017

Volunteered as a Science Fair Judge for the Southwest Washington Science and Engineering Fair.

Invited by Pleasant Mountain Elementary School to participate in a career fair as the resident scientist for elementary and middle school students, November 2016

Invited by nPower Girls program to lecture Kalama High School ninth grade students regarding a career in applied ecology, and what occurs in the typical day of a scientist, November 2016.

Volunteer plankton expert at the Vancouver Lake Ecoblitz, October 2016.

Volunteer facilitator at the March 2016 Watershed Congress, providing feedback and leadership for elementary and middle school students working on watershed monitoring in Clark County, May 2016 Invited to participate in a panel to speak to high school students at the Clark College iTech program about the process of acquiring a college degree, February 2016

Student Representative on Tree Committee at Washington State University, 2014 – 2016

President and Founder of the Environmental Science and Sustainability Club at WSU, helping to organize meetings, events, and logistics to connect students to the campus and improve campus sustainability, 2013 - 2016

Nominated to participate in town hall meetings with Governor Inslee in to discuss proposed legislation that will address climate change in Washington State, April & December 2015

Invited to participate in a meeting with Washington State University Board of Regents to discuss my experience at WSU as a woman in STEM, November 2016

Invited to host the Student Leadership Recognition Award Ceremony to announce student accomplishments and facilitate ceremony, November 2015

Volunteer at Sacred Sueños in Vilcabamba, Ecuador, learned permaculture design and assisted in goat care and cheese making, cob construction, and farm maintenance, May 2014

Founded the Portland, Oregon chapter of Citizens Climate Lobby, traveled to Washington DC to meet with members of Congress to discuss a carbon fee and dividend, 2012

Member of Environmental Club at Clark College, assisted in the acquisition of a grant to install a compost system in the cafeteria, 2011 - 2012

Volunteered with NERD Girls at Clark College, engaging in community STEM outreach for middle and high school aged students, 2011

Volunteer for State Senator Brian Baird, engaging the community through door knocking and phone campaigns, 2004

Volunteer with SOLVE Oregon Beach Clean Up, 1999 – 2002

## **GRANTS & HONORS**

Best Poster award at American Water Resource Association MT conference, October 2019

CUAHSI Let's Talk About Water Challenge Grant, January 2019

NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Fellow, March 2018

Montana Water Center Student Fellow, March 2018

Banner carrier for the Washington State University College of Arts and Sciences, May 2017 1st Place Research Presentation, Air & Waste Management Association Oregon Chapter Student

Environmental Challenge, April 2017

NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Honorable Mention, March 2017

Clark County Public Works Innovation Award for work in Local Source Control, February 2017

Best Undergraduate Research Poster, Washington State University Research Showcase, November 2016

President's Honor Roll in 2013 - 2016

University Scholars Honors Program at Washington State University Vancouver, October 2015

NSF Research Experience for Undergraduates Fellowship, June 2015

John Robert Brown Scholarship, November 2015

Student Leadership Recognition Award, November 2015

Vancouver Watershed Alliance grant as part of Environmental Club at Clark College, October 2012

WORKSHOPS & NSF Cross-INFEWS NRT meeting, July 31 – August 1, 2018. "Building a collaborative vision and diverse **CERTIFICATIONS** community to support the emerging FEWS workforce", Missoula, Montana.

> Participated in the National Education for Women (NEW) Leadership Summer Institute gaining experience in public speaking, organizing, and message management, drawing on the expertise of women in various fields, and preparing for political leadership, July 2016

Certified Watershed Steward in Clark County, which required an eight-week training and engaging in volunteer events that were beneficial for watershed vitality, 2013

**SCIENTIFIC** 

SOCIETY

Society for Freshwater Science, 2019 - present American Geophysical Union, 2018 - 2020

**MEMBERSHIPS** 

Sigma Xi, 2018 - 2019

Graduate Women in Science, 2017 - present Associate Women in Science, 2017 - 2019

American Water Resources Association Montana, 2017 – present

# **HOBBIES**

INTERESTS AND Hiking, rock climbing, surfing, camping, travel, sewing, cooking, sailing, gardening, mushroom harvesting, live music, and science fiction books.